<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jingyushi.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jingyushi.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-17T06:46:17+00:00</updated><id>https://jingyushi.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jingyu Shi</title><entry><title type="html">On Traveling</title><link href="https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2025/ontraveling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Traveling"/><published>2025-09-24T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-24T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2025/ontraveling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2025/ontraveling/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/facai-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/facai-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/facai-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/facai.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Wingman (Facai) and Yuumi under my bed. </div> <p>I like travelling.</p> <p>I like travelling when I can just stay up late talking with people whom I enjoy talking to and who enjoy talking to me too. I like travelling when I do not have to get up early the next morning just to catch a bus or a flight to some places crowded with tourists. I like travelling when I do not have to suffacated in the crowd or rot in a long queue just to see something “famous”, when I can share the moments with somebody who enjoys escaping from what traps us in our daily life and the confirmation that this very person or these very group of people enjoy this moment ridicularly the same much as I do, and when I witness how life can be both different and the same for people from different culture backgrounds.</p> <p>The more I travel and meet people, the more I realize that we are much more alike than different. There is equal amount of depression in ordinary you and me, whether we are Chinese, European, or American, regardless of what architectural style our buildings are, no matter how much we pay for gas at the gas station. Life sucks for everybody. Life is great for everybody. It just depends on the day. The core of humanity is to suffer and to have some fun suffering. As Albert Camus once said, one must imagine Sisyphus happy.</p> <p>Instead of drowning into the voidness and meaninglessness of life anywhere on earth, I wanna show my regrets for not travelling enough, /(It will never be enough, because the world is too big and we are too small./) since it is somewhat impossible for me to travel outside of the US again until I finish my degree. But I believe I will hit the road again someday in the future.</p> <p align="center"> <img src="/assets/img/copenhagen.JPG" width="512"/> <figcaption>In Copenhagen with the Little Mermaid.</figcaption> </p> <p align="center"> <img src="/assets/img/interlaken.JPG" width="512"/> <figcaption>In Interlaken waiting for my train.</figcaption> </p> <p align="center"> <img src="/assets/img/prague.JPG" width="512"/> </p> <p align="center"> <img src="/assets/img/prague2.JPG" width="512"/> <figcaption>In Prague. Photos taken by a friend of mine, whom I had known since middle high, but had not met for four years.</figcaption> </p> <p align="center"> <img src="/assets/img/paris.JPG" width="512"/> <figcaption>In Paris. The Eiffel Tower. I went there mid-night just to avoid the crowd.</figcaption> </p> <p align="center"> <img src="/assets/img/rome.JPG" width="512"/> <figcaption>Hungover in Rome. I woke up with vomits in the restroom. I went so blackout that I thought it was someone else but me.</figcaption> </p> <p align="center"> <img src="/assets/img/rome2.JPG" width="512"/> <figcaption>In the Colosseum.</figcaption> </p> <p align="center"> <img src="/assets/img/rome3.JPG" width="512"/> <figcaption>By the Trevi Fountain.</figcaption> </p> <p align="center"> <img src="/assets/img/rome4.JPG" width="512"/> <figcaption>In the Colosseum with my folks.</figcaption> </p> <p align="center"> <img src="/assets/img/strasbourg.JPG" width="512"/> <figcaption>In Strasbourg, meeting my primary school friend Max since eight or nine years. Can you imagine?</figcaption> </p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some personal feelings about traveling.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fighting the Imposter Syndrome</title><link href="https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2024/imposter_syndrome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fighting the Imposter Syndrome"/><published>2024-06-15T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-15T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2024/imposter_syndrome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2024/imposter_syndrome/"><![CDATA[<p>Impostor syndrome, also known as the imposter phenomenon, is a psychological pattern where individuals experience persistent self-doubt and the inability to believe their successes are deserved. Despite evidence of their competence and accomplishments, they may feel like frauds and fear being “found out”.</p> <p>For me, it all started when I began my journey of pursuing my PhD. Whenever I speak to my friend or tell a new folk that I am doing my PhD, they will almost greet me with their immediate praise like ‘who you must be very smart’ or ‘you must know a lot’. In the very beginning, it was motivating and rewarding. Back then (probably in the first one or two years of my PhD), I thought it was true. I thought I was smart and knew a lot. But being in the community of all these great minds and peers for a couple of years, I kind of lost the ability to take the credit for myself.</p> <p>I might have prepared myself well for this imposter syndrome, with which I never feel I am good enough to take all the credits people give me. I did my undergrad in Beihang University, which is one block away from Tsinghua University, the best university in China. We had a saying (or my own theory) that no matter how good I was at whatever subject, there would always be somebody in Tsinghua who was better than me at that subject and any other subject possible. I must say that this might sound like a loser mindset, but it did prepare me well and humble me enough to not get flattered too much during my PhD.</p> <p>I appreciated myself for acknowledging others’ intelligence. A PhD or doing PhD does not mean that I am smart. It is merely a career. I fought the stereotype people have towards PhD. It can easily get people (PhDs) too flattered and thus too ignorant and cocky. But the tricky part is that humbling myself can also lead to the downfall of my self recognition. In the past two years, I kept asking myself questions like ‘what am I really good at?’, ‘What can I achieve?’, or ‘Am I really doing anything with my life?’, because I looked up to the folks who were so successful with their academic journeys and folks who were making every right decisions in their careers. They wrote better codes, their designed better algorithms, their made more money, they published better papers, and they lived a better life. At some point, I was so humbled that I started questioning the point of my life, why I was doing whatever I was doing. While other folks praising me for being good at what I did, I almost instantly denied their acknowledgement in my mind and labelled myself as lucky or pretentious or whatever excuses for the slightest achievement I had.</p> <p>This is definitely a dangerous mindset, with which I no longer reward myself for achieving goals. But the decision I made is to stay humble. I came to realize that even folks who seemed ahead of me (academically or personally or physically or anyhow) also suffered from their own imposter syndrome because there are always somebody to look up to and to envy. Maybe they are the imposters they think they are. Maybe I am the imposter I think I am. I would rather stay humbled and push myself to those who I look up to than be cocky. If I humble myself, no one can humble me. Maybe there is no fighting the imposter syndrome. There is merely me feeling the need to be better. But truth be told, getting a PhD does not mean that someone is smart or knowledgeable. I hate feeling superior just because of a PhD title or even simply doing PhD, not to mention how I feel about folks who do.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fighting the Imposter Syndrome]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ChatGPT as a Reviewer</title><link href="https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2023/gptreviewer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ChatGPT as a Reviewer"/><published>2023-11-19T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-19T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2023/gptreviewer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2023/gptreviewer/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/yuumioncar-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/yuumioncar-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/yuumioncar-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/yuumioncar.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Yuumi on my car. </div> <p>A very useful tips of ChatGPT 4: We can use it as an external reviewers for our own papers. This is a very recent finding of mine along my way of writing reviews. I used ChatGPT as an assistant (please do not have it write it all for you, which is clearly forbidden). I noticed that despite the fact that it clear does not posses a humanoid taste of HCI or general CS research and high-level thinking that critically assesses a piece of research (which is why we are needed), it suffices to provide logical critique and importantly it can critically evaluate the evaluation sections of papers. It can reveal whether our papers are well-written enough to make people understand the logic and flow of the thinking behind the characters. It can also tell whether there are flaws in the statistical tests we used and what kind of tests we should have done if flaws exist. It tells us what is missing to prove every point we’ve made in the paper. Since it is prompt-based communication, we can actually adjust the difficulty of ChatGPT as our reviewers of the paper by telling it to be more critical (mostly likely, get prepared for the worst) or more generous (less preferred tho). The best about ChatGPT as an external reviewer is that it is always a third opinion. Once you open up a new dialogue it loses its memory about your previous discussion and it gets to reassess your paper as if it’s never read it before. We know what is critical of our manuscripts, if the same concerns keep showing up in this iterations.</p> <p>IMO, peer-review system is always a game of luck. We will still need to roll the dice even if the paper is complete. But what does it take to make the paper complete? I believe that the dice would not be fair until we make our manuscript to a level where the logic is seamless, the stats are solid, and the presentations are connective and good, or as good as we can be. Then the reviewers can only criticize the ideas. The whole point is to shrink the space where they can attack our submissions. We cannot control whether they like the idea or not but the completeness of the paper. I suggest everyone try using ChatGPT to write a review of our own paper once and we will see how helpful it is.</p> <p>BTW, if you are writing reviews for others using ChatGPT, please make sure you read and write the very first version without the help of ChatGPT or do not use ChatGPT at all (please strictly follow the protocal of writing a review). The closure of thinking is what matters here afterall. Otherwise, it will ruin the whole point of a peer-review system.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="academic"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ChatGPT as a Reviewer]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Taste in Human-AI Interaction</title><link href="https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2023/mytasteinHAI/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Taste in Human-AI Interaction"/><published>2023-10-30T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-30T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2023/mytasteinHAI</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2023/mytasteinHAI/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/momo-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/momo-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/momo-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/momo.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Momo under my chair. </div> <p>As a Ph.D. student who had had no experience in HCI research before, I suffered a lot when I was trying to transit my ways of thinking from an AI developer (or say a Machine Learning engineer or a Deep Learning engineer?) to an HCI researcher. My suffering majorly resulted from the fact that I did not know what was held dear in the HCI community (and that I had not formed a taste of research in general myself). Never, do I dare to announce my expertise at solving HCI problems, yet I wish to summarize some points that might contribute to anyone who are interested in both topics (AI and HCI) and my take-aways through my learning and scattered moments of Eureka.</p> <p>The very first thing I realized was that HCI or Human-AI Interaction (HAII, I might use them interchangably but I meant HAII mostly, but some claims can be generalized to the broad topic of HCI. I would slack off here a bit to welcome some thinking.) research emphased more on the functionality and functions of a computing or an AI system, while AI research preferred the performance over an specific problem or task or the abilities to solve novel forms of problems and tasks. Of course, I am not asserting that exclusively HCI research does not care about performance or AI research is not functional, but rather pointing out an interesting phenomenon or say difference between HCI and AI that is induced by the very essences of both topics: When we talk about AI alone, we do not bring in the human factor. And when human factors are involved, researchers have to bring in a whole different set of <strong>metrics</strong> to evaluate the systems. Such <strong>metrics</strong> tend to be diverse and unaligned, because humans, as compared to (existing) computing systems, are way too complex and dynamic, not to mentioned when human factors are to be considered across diverse contexts or tasks.</p> <p>What are these metrics? To answer this question, I would like to go back to the functionality and functions of a computing/AI system aforementioned. I define functionality as the inherent quality of a system to work for some purposes of some users, while functions as the nuanced capabilities of a system to accomplish some specific tasks. For example, an image classification network has the function to classify a given image, but it does not have the functionality to work for image classification purposes until an integrated system is developed to allow some target users to use all the functions with an interface.</p> <p>Metaphorically, let’s say HCI is the design of using some tool and AI is the function of the tool. Consider a hammer, where the head is AI, with which we smash (functions), the handle is the HCI design, and the ideology that the momentum of the head can be increased by grabbing and swinging the handle (functionality) is the utimate principle that we follow to make a tool <strong>usable</strong>. To assess the functionality and functions of a computing, <strong>metrics</strong> are designed.</p> <p>How do we design better heads and better handles for hammers? This question sounds easy if we seperate the heads and the handles - On the one hand, we can improve the performance of the AI on the specific task by introducing novel architectures, better algorithms, or utilizing more information. On the other hand, we can make the handles more human-friendly by designing more intuitive interfaces, increasing the system usability, or making it adaptive to a larger user groups. However, but the principle that we are following couples the heads and the handles and therefore complicates the problem. It is impossible (or at least constrained by strong assumptions) to consider the heads without considering the handles. E.g. the specific tasks have to be meaningful to certain users in some impactful real-world problems. More frequently, designing the handles depends on the heads. The interactions to be enabled by the systems are dependent of the functions of the AI models/algorithms, and the more coupled systems allow deeper interactions with the architecture.</p> <p>I personally discover that there exists a trade-off between the depth of the HAII and the user-friendliness of the HAII. When interactions that allow users to tweak or modify the architecture, the algorithms, or the mechanism of an AI system, they shrink the possible user groups because of the expertise in AI they require. Put simply, interactions that change the AI performance require the users to know what their actions lead to, i.e. they know how AI works.</p> <p>Is there anyway of allowing users interact deeply with the AI without expertise? Yes, and I think that is the very core and essence of HAII research, which is to map the human-intuitive interactions to complex interactions that changes the AI. For the users, they only need to do simple actions that, in their expectation, will lead to some results. The tasks for HAII researchers are</p> <ul> <li>to model the mapping between the human-intuitive interactions to the change in the AI mechanism,</li> <li>and build a surrogate model that depicts the cognitive mapping between the human input and their expectation of output (not the value of the output but the form and mechanism of the output).</li> </ul> <p>I will come up with an example to better depict what I mean here. But going back the point that the HAII problems are coupled by the factors of the AI functionality and functions and interaction principles, I would like to assert a gap that I identify between current research and the future of HAII: the research of AI and the research of HAII are decoupled. Communities follow different metrics, which I am not saying is wrong, but merely questioning the existence of a possible general framework that considers not only the performance of an AI model on tasks but also its usability in the context of the designated tasks? Envisioning this framework, I think decoupled research is not enough. What we have been doing is like digging up a tunnel from two sides (AI and HCI) of a mountain, with no guarantee that the two sides will meet. What if they do not meet? (I do not know) What should be done to align or share the interests of both sides to guarantee or foster a convergence?</p> <p>draft:</p> <ul> <li>the capabilities of AI systems solving novel tasks enable new domains to explore in HCI</li> <li>how well under some measurement should a computing system perform in a task to be considered <strong>usable</strong>? What is the definition of <strong>usable</strong>. To be continued…</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What I see and not see from the current research in human-AI interaction.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Proclaimation 10043 And I</title><link href="https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2023/10043/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Proclaimation 10043 And I"/><published>2023-10-27T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-27T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2023/10043</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jingyushi.github.io/blog/2023/10043/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/10043-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/10043-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/10043-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/10043.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The trick is not minding. </div> <h1 id="background">Background</h1> <p>Proclamation 10043 is a presidential proclaimation signed by Donald Trump, the 45th US president, on May 29, 2020, in order to prohibit students in the People’s Republic of China associated with the People’s Liberation Army from obtaining F visas or J visas.</p> <h1 id="my-story">My story</h1> <p>I have always been an enthusiast of oversea traveling and studying abroad. I set my goal as early as junior high to pursue a degree or more in a foreign country. I have been to tons of countries and visited the most prestigious univeristies of the lands. I have seen and heard enough to make my decision to pursuit graduate degrees in the most advance (in tech and science) and the richest country of human-history, the US. I said good riddance to my beloved lalaland of <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Chengdu,+Sichuan,+China/@30.6587199,103.9107381,11z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m6!3m5!1s0x36efc52300447721:0xb98652ce2e240e02!8m2!3d30.5722599!4d104.0665099!16zL20vMDE2djQ2?entry=ttu">Chengdu City</a> and left for Atlanta after four years of undergraduate study in Beihang University, the students of which were unfortuanately forbidden to renew their F-visa due to Proclaimation 10043 since May 2020.</p> <p>I do not intend to talk about the politics here but rather to provide a first-person view of what this proclaimation has brought to a foreign student, who cannot go back home until he finishes his Ph.D. program or would otherwise never be allowed back to the US again with a valid student visa. History and politics always have the power to disrupt, disturb, or even destroy the lives of individuals. Never sensitive to politics, the only thing I realized was that barrier being built between me and the word ‘home’. It has been four years since I saw my parents in person and so as my friends, and I know it just started and it will be a longer journey than I can expect.</p> <p>Being in the last generation from my alma mater that went to the US for a degree, my alumni are getting lesser by years. I sometimes talked with them about their takes on their being and life. Surprisingly, they all had the same dreams as mine, where we went home and saw our family finally, but panicked when we realized that we could not make it back to the US for our degrees. I found the coincidences rather interesting, yet moreover, misteriously comforting. After all, my friends and alumni who later became friends with me for fighting the same situations, are all on the same page of life. I realize how supported I can feel to see people standing by me, sharing my fear, and fighting the same monster under our beds. This is a stronger bond that I never experience before, that I share with someone I barely have connection with.</p> <p>However, I never really feared like some of my ‘comrades’, who may cry, fight, or struggle to <a href="https://www.10043.org/">show their opposition to the policy</a>. I guess I am just numb. I never think about what consequences it may bring. Unlike many fellas of my age, I never experience the loss of elder family members like grandparents. My grandparents are still in good shape. It is sad that people may go. It is even sadder when I never realize this or experience this and therefore have to guess. How does it feel to lose someone close in life forever? How does it feel to lose friendship and memory of hometown due to incapability of maintenance? So many unresolved questions and unknown experiences about my future. If they are gonna be sad, I wish I had experienced them early. With that being said, do I really want my grandparent gone before I left for my education, so that I get to stay with them when they do? Am I this pathetic, or is it the proclaimation that is twisting my thoughts and feelings and making me a pathetic monster? I do not know the answers. I do not dare to know. All I can do is pretend that it never bothers and numb and hammer myself with stuffs, work, study, research, and sometimes video games.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal"/><category term="writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What Proclaimation 10043 has brought to me.]]></summary></entry></feed>